Finding Aid for Carl M. Weideman Papers 1921-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carl M. Weideman Papers 1921-1972 1932-1934
Weideman, Carl May, 1898-1972.
Detroit, Michigan trial attorney, Democratic Congressman, 1933-1935, and Wayne County Circuit Court Judge. Correspondence and other materials concerning his term in Congress, national and local politics, and various judicial decisions; miscellaneous diaries, newspaper clippings, and scrapbooks concerning his association with the American Turners Association (German-American athletic society), Detroit, Michigan politics, and the election and recall of Detroit Mayor Charles Bowles; and photographs.
86360 Aa 2; UAm; AC
3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Weideman (donor no. 5265 ) and came to the library in 1972.
The collection is open for research.
Carl M. Weideman was born in Detroit, Michigan on March 5, 1898. He was a student at the University of Michigan from 1914 to 1916. With the outbreak of World War I, he attended the Naval Officers Training School, then enlisted in the United States Navy as an apprentice seaman. From 1918 to 1922, he was a member of the United States Naval Reserve. For much of this time, Weideman was able to continue his studies, graduating from the Detroit College of Law in 1921.
Weideman was a successful trial attorney throughout the 1920s and early 1930s. In 1932 he became politically active winning election to the U.S. House of Representatives from Michigan's 14th Congressional District, which included Detroit's east side and the Grosse Pointes. While serving in Congress, he was a member of the Immigration and Naturalization, District of Columbia, and Un-American Activities committees. Weideman was a one-term Congressman failing to receive his party's nomination for re-election in 1934. He was elected a Wayne County Circuit Court commissioner in 1936 and served in that position until 1950 when he was appointed to the Wayne County Circuit bench by Governor G. Mennen Williams. He retired from the bench in 1969.
Weideman was active in various professional and civic organizations. He was a long-time member of the American Turners serving as national president from 1937 to 1952. He died March 5, 1972.
The collection consists of correspondence, primarily from the period when Weideman was a member of Congress; files relating to his election campaign and to a few of the issues of the time; and miscellaneous other materials from his career with the Wayne County Circuit Court and as a member of the American Turners. There is also an extensive series of scrapbooks detailing his professional and civic activities and several folders of photographs.
Subjects:
American Turners (Organization); Athletics--Michigan--Detroit.; Bowles, Charles, 1884-1957.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); German Americans--Michigan.; Judges--Michigan--Wayne County.; Michigan. Circuit Court (Wayne County); New Deal, 1933-1939.; Strikes and lockouts--Michigan--Detroit.; United States. Congress.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1932.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1934.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; Weideman, Carl May, 1898-1972.
Subjects - Visual Material:
American Turners (Organization); Boats.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Detroit.; Butchers--Michigan--Detroit.; Dance.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Detroit (Mich.)--Butchers.; Dogs.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; German Americans.; Interiors.; Oaths.; Politics & government.; United States. Congress. House.; Weideman, Carl May, 1898-1972.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Contributors:
Abbott, Horatio J. (Horatio Johnson), 1876-1936; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Bushnell, George E. (George Edward), 1887-1965.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Coughlin, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1891-1979.; Debo, Alfred.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Foley, Thomas.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Hubbard, Orville Liscum, 1903-1982.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952.; Jeffries, Edward J., 1864-1939.; Jeffries, Edward, 1900-1950; Joy, Henry Bourne, 1864-1936.; Lacy, Arthur J. (Arthur Jay), 1876-1975.; Lesinski, John, 1885-1950.; Martel, Frank Xavier, 1888-; O'Brien, Patrick H. (Patrick Henry), 1868-1959; Perkins, Frances, 1882-1965.; Piggins, Edward S., d. 1972.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Tugwell, Rexford G. (Rexford Guy), 1891-1979; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - September 1932-1934, 21 folders (Box 1)
  - 1935-1947, 6 folders (Box 1)
- Campaign and Congressional Files
  - 1932 election campaign (Box 1)
  - 1933
    - Congressional voting record (Box 1)
    - Briggs Strike in Detroit (Box 1)
    - St. Lawrence Seaway (Box 1)
    - Michigan Naturalization Plan circa 1933 (Box 2)
  - 1934
    - Horatio Abbott and Michigan patronage (Box 2)
    - Bill to provide compensation to an American Indian (H.R. 7543) (Box 2)
    - Arthur Lacy's campaign for governor in Michigan (Box 2)
    - "Dawn Patrol" (Box 2)
      (alleged anti-union spy, agency)
    - Re-election campaign (Box 2)
- Later Activities
  - Election as Wayne County Court Commissioner 1935 (Box 2)
  - Concerning appointment as Wayne County Circuit Court Judge 1950 (Box 2)
  - Concerning Wayne County Circuit Court election 1959 (Box 2)
  - Concerning Wayne County Circuit Court 1950s undated (Box 2)
- Litigation files
  - "Weideman vs. Heston" 1921, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - "Weideman vs. The Detroit News" 1933 (Box 2)
  - "Weideman vs. the County of Wayne" 1971 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - American Turners Association (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Biographies and obituaries (Box 2)
  - Diaries, 1930-1931, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    (brief entries)
- Photographs
  (see also oversize UAm folder)
  - Awards, bill signings, etc., 2 envelopes (Box 2)
  - Early photos (Box 2)
  - Informal photos; with wife and others (Box 2)
  - Parents' butcher shop in Detroit (Box 2)
  - Portraits (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1921-1929 (Box 3)
  - 1928-1931 (Volume 1)
    (concerning Detroit politics, particularly the election and recall of Detroit Mayor, Charles Bowles)
  - 1933-1939 (Box 3)
    (concerning the American Turners)
  - 1948 (Box 3)
  - 1945 (Box 3)
  - 1946-1951 (Box 3)
    (including material concerning the Detroit Lawyers Guild)
  - 1951-1955 (Volume 2)
  - 1950-1957 (Box 3)
  - 1959 (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Abbott, Horatio Johnson
May 31, 1933, Aug. 14, 1944 and Jan. 29, 1934
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-
May 19, 1933, Aug. 16, 1933, and Apr. 24, 1942
Bushnell, George Edward, 1887-1965.
1933 and Feb. 13, 1934
Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.
Nov. 8, 1933 and Dec. 22, 1933
Coughlin, Charles Edward, 1891-
Mar. 15, 1933, May 23, 1933, Jan. 3, 1934 and Dec. 29, 1934
Debo, Alfred
May 31, 1933 and Jan. 29, 1934
Farley, James Aloysius, 1888-
Mar. 31, 1933, July 14, 1933, Sept. 1, 1933 and Oct. 24, 1933
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.
Jan. 22, 1934
Foley, Thomas
Oct. 1, 1971
Hoover, J. Edgar, 1895-1972.
Dec. 1, 1933
Hubbard, Orville L.
Oct. 10, 1952
Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.
Oct. 3, 1933
Ickes, Harold L., 1874-1952
Mar. 20, 1934
Jeffries, Edward J., 1900-1950.
Mar. 18, 1933
Jeffries, Edward J.
May 5, 1933
Joy, Henry Bourne, 1864-1936.
Apr. 27, 1933
Lacy, Arthur Jay, 1876-
June 15, 1934
Lesinski, John, 1885-1950.
Oct. 30, 1933
Martell, Frank Xavier, 1888-
1933, Mar. 20, 1934, Apr. 20, 1934 and Jan. 31, 1934
O'Brien, Patrick Henry, 1868-1959.
May 1, 1933, June 23, 1933, May 22, 1934
Perkins, Frances, 1882-1965.
May 31, 1933
Piggins, Edward S.
Aug. 15, 1958
Romney, George Wilcken, 1907-
Sept. 30, 1968
Tugwell, Rexford Guy, 1891-
Feb. 21, 1934
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Oct. 12, 1933 and Dec. 4, 1933